Guide to the Stanton Wheeler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stanton Wheeler Papers
1950-2004
MS 1954
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
45.25
(62 boxes)
The papers document Stanton Wheeler's professional career at the Yale Law School and include teaching files from courses he taught at Yale; correspondence; drafts of publications and other writings; files pertaining to his scholarly research interests; and files related to Wheeler's involvement with committees and professional organizations.
Wheeler, Stanton, 1930-
Conditions Governing Access
The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks. Student records in the original records will remain closed until 2082.
Additional material contained in accession 2012-M-003 is open to researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Stanton Wheeler was born on September 27, 1930, in Pomona, California. He was educated at Pomona College, where he graduated with a bachelor's degree in sociology in 1952, and subsequently earned both a master's and doctorate in sociology from the University of Washington in 1956 and 1958 respectively. In 1958, Dr. Wheeler joined the faculty of the Department of Social Relations at Harvard University, and in 1960 he took a leave of absence to serve as a Fulbright Research Scholar at the Institutes of Sociology and Criminology at the University of Oslo, Norway. Dr. Wheeler returned to Harvard in 1961 and continued there as an Assistant Professor until 1963, when he left to become an Associate Professor in the Department of Sociology at the University of Washington. From 1966 to 1968, he was an Adjunct Assistant Professor of Law and Sociology at Yale University, and in 1968 he joined the faculty of the Yale Law School as Professor of Law and Sociology, a position he held for the remainder of his career.
Stanton Wheeler was notable for being one of the first professors at an American law school who did not hold a law degree. His research and teaching interests included white collar crime, prison systems, juvenile delinquency, the sociology of law, sports law, and music law. He was the author of ten books, as well as many published articles. In addition to teaching at the Yale Law School, Dr. Wheeler also served for many years as Master of Morse College, one of Yale's undergraduate residence halls. Stanton Wheeler died on December 7, 2007, at the age of 77.
Scope and Contents
The papers document Stanton Wheeler's professional career at the Yale Law School and include teaching files from courses he taught at Yale; correspondence; drafts of publications and other writings; files pertaining to his scholarly research interests; and files related to Wheeler's involvement with committees and professional organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marcia A. Chambers, 2007 and 2011.
Arrangement
Materials arranged by accession.
Sports -- Law and legislation; White collar crimes; Sociologists; Wheeler, Stanton, 1930-; Yale Law School
- Original accession, circa 1950-2000; 30.75
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks. Student records closed until 2082.
  Arrangement
  Materials in this accession are arranged as received.
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this accession consist entirely of teaching files pertaining to courses taught by Stanton Wheeler at the Yale Law School. Specific course topics documented in the materials include sports and the law; the sociology of sports; white collar crime; and music and the law.
  - Sports and the law course materials (Box 1)
  - Sports and social policy course materials (Box 1)
  - Faculty committee on athletics records (Box 2)
  - Faculty committee on athletics records (Box 3)
  - Sports and the law: general (Box 4)
  - General information on college athletics (Box 4)
  - Sports and the law: course materials (Box 5)
  - Sports and the law: articles (Box 5)
  - Sports and the law: course materials (Box 6)
  - Sports and the law: academic articles (Box 7)
  - Sports and the law: interviews (Box 7)
  - Sports and the law: miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Sociology of sports: articles (Box 8)
  - Sociology of sports: course materials (Box 8)
  - Faculty committee on athletics records (Box 9)
  - Amateur Athletic Foundation Records (Box 10)
  - Sentencing study: interviews with judges (Box 11)
  - State supreme court project (Box 12)
  - White collar crime sentencing study (Box 12)
  - Sentencing study: interviews with judges (Box 13)
  - White collar crime: general (Box 14)
  - White collar crime: course materials (Box 15)
  - White collar crime: course materials (Box 16)
  - White collar crime: news reports (Box 16)
  - Music and the law: course materials (Box 17)
  - Music and the law: course materials (Box 18)
  - Crime and criminal justice course materials (Box 19)
  - Music and the law: course materials (Box 20)
  - Prison riot studies (Box 21)
  - Music law: general (Box 21)
  - Entertainment law: general (Box 21)
  - Law and society: course materials (Box 22)
  - Sociology (Box 23)
  - Crime and criminal justice (Box 24)
  - Student records (Box 25)
    Student records closed until January 1, 2082.
  - Bibliographical information (Box 26)
  - Law school (Box 26)
  - Music at Yale (Box 26)
  - Yale Law School clinics files (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 30)
  - People files (Box 31)
  - Subject files (Box 31)
  - AAF (Box 32)
  - Russell Sage (Box 32)
  - Drafts for publications (Box 32)
  - Morse College (Box 32)
- Additional material, 1962-2004; Accession 2012-M-003
  This accession includes files and correspondence related to Stanton Wheeler's scholarship and teaching on the topics of prisons, white collar crime, state supreme courts, and sentencing. Also included are files on collegiate athletics, including his involvement with the Yale Faculty Committee on Athletics.
  Materials in this accession are grouped together according to document type, and are thereafter arranged alphabetically.
  - Chronological files
    - 1981 Mar-Dec, 1981-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - 1982 Aug-1983 Aug, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Professional correspondence
    - General
      - 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Alphabetical
      - Ashbrook, John M., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Bailey, F. Lee, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Bell, Merlyn Matthews, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Clark, Robert, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        General
        Includes research proposal appendices.
      - Friedman, Lawrence, 1972-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        Includes notes and manuscript draft.
      - Harris, Peter, 1978, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Hausmann, Henry, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Includes manuscript draft.
      - Katz, Jack, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Larson, Otto N., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Lempert, Richard, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Levin, Richard C., 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Lindblom, Charles E., 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Lipson, Leon S., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Loh, Wallace, 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Includes manuscript.
      - "M" miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Martin, John P., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Monahan, John, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Moore, Mark H., 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        Includes National Science Foundation proposal and manuscripts on white collar crime.
        See also:White collar crime.
      - "N" miscellaneous, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        Folder removed for mold remediation.
      - Nagel, Irene, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Parrish, Bill, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Polsby, Nelson, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Posner, Richard, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Public Interest Law Project, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Quigley, John, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - "R" miscellaneous, 1967-1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Reisman, Michael, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 19)
        Includes notes and draft manuscripts.
      - Rose-Ackerman, Susan, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Rothman, Mitchell, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Sarat, Austin, 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Shapiro, Susan, 1976-1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Simon, John, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Sports, 1977-1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "T" miscellaneous, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        folder removed for mold remediation.
      - Tyler, Harold, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "U" miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - University of Massachusetts at Amherst, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "V" miscellaneous, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "W" miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Weisburd, David, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Wellford, Charles, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
        Includes research proposal.
      - Wellington, Harry, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Wheeler, Stanton
        - Incoming, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 14)
        - Outgoing, 1983 January-June (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Wolpin, Kenneth I., 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 16)
        Includes vita and manuscripts.
      - "Y" miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "Z" miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Zunno, Frank, 1969-1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Chronological, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 4-8)
  - Professional files
    - Conferences
      - Committee on Law and Justice, Annual Conference, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Institution for Social and Policy Studies (ISPS) Decision Making Seminar, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
      - LASA Meetings, 1984 June (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Law and Society Association
        - Meeting, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Executive committee meeting, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - National Research Council meeting, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Resource Center for Consumers of Legal Services Conference, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Seven Springs Conference, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
        See also: White Collar Crime.
        - Legal Ethics Symposia, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Society for the Study of Social Problems annual meeting, 1975 August (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Sociology of Judicial Process Conference, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Stanford Conference on Due Process, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Criminology
      - Classroom materials, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
      - Statistical tests for discrimination, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Uniform crime reporting, 1962-1963, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Victims of crimes, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Women on patrol, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Organizations
      - American Arbitration Association, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Committee for the Study of Incarceration, 1973-1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Committee on Law and Social Science, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - International Sociological Association, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Law and Society Association, 1970-1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - National Academy of Sciences, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - National Research Council: Committee on Behavioral and Social Sciences and Education, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Russell Sage Foundation
        - 1977-1982 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
        - National Research Council proposal, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - House testimony, Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Social Science Research Council
        - 1975-1978 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - 1975-1982 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
      - Sociological Research Association, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Prisons
      - Prison research -- Nuffield College, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Scandinavian prison study, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Site visit, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Vermont Department of Corrections, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Privacy, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Sentencing
      - American Bar Association -- "price fixing", 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Bode research data and correspondence, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Criminal anti-trust cases, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Judicial reaction to sentencing guidelines, 1979-1988 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Paper label sentencing, 1977, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Parole prediction case, 1973, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Parole and sentencing workshop, 1974-1976 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Public access to information, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Sentencing -- summer work, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Sentencing Behavior Study
        - Administrative offices of the U.S. courts, 1979-1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
        - Bureau of Prisons and Probation Department, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 11)
        - Data analysis, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
        - Draft, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 13)
        - Sentencing behavior memoranda
          - 1-13, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 14)
          - 14-25, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 1)
          - 26-37, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 2)
          - 38-49, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 3)
          - 50-65, 1980-1981 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        - Wheeler/Weisburd/Bode files
          - #1, 1971-1979 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
          - #2, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Sentencing progress report (patterns and behavior), Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Sentencing reform
        - 1977-1982 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
        - Workshop, 1974-1978 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
      - "Sentencing the White Collar Offender: Rhetoric and Reality", Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - State Supreme Court
      - "Business of State Supreme Courts", Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Evolution of State Supreme Courts, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
      - State Supreme Court Project
        - Coding materials, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
        - Policy manual, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        - Production code, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Progress report, 1976, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - Research proposal
          - 1973-1975 (Box 17, Folder 3)
          - 1977-1978 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Statistics on crime, Undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - White collar crime
      See also: Faculty seminars, box 24, folders 4-16.
      See also: Seven Springs Conference, box 8, folders 1-4.
      See also: Moore, Mark H., box 4, folder 10.
      - Accounting and white collar crime, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 6-7)
      - Analysis memoranda
        - 1-43, 1980, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - 44-65, 1980, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Conference on White-Collar Illegality, 1974, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Encyclopedia article, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Freedom of Information requests, 1978-1980 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
      - Friedman draft publications, 1975-1977 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Legal Defense of White Collar Crime -- manuscript draft, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - Litigation in small claims court, 1973-1980 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Mann manuscripts, correspondence, and field notes, 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - "Organizational Illegality", 1977-1981 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Papers -- general, 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Program in Criminal Justice
        - Grant adjustment notices, 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Initial grant request, 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 5-6)
        - No-cost extensions
          - 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 7)
          - 1980, 1980-1980 (Box 19, Folder 8)
          - 1980-1981 (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - Renewal application, 1978-1980 (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Renewal application (withdrawn), 1977-1979 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
        - Renewal negotiations correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Readings, 1982, undated (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
      - Research agenda, 1976-1977 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Rothman research materials and manuscripts, 1981-1982 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Shapiro, Susan - research and draft manuscripts, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
      - Social History of White Collar Crime, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Studies in White Collar Crime, 1976, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
        A brief description of the program.
      - Subcommittee on Crime -- corporate questionnaire, 1979 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - United Nations -- Interregional meeting, 1978-1979 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
      - White Collar Crime and Social Policy Seminar, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - White collar crime defense practice, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - White Collar Crime Planning Workshop, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - White collar crime study review, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - White collar illegality, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - "White Collar Illegality: The Need for Research", 1979 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Yale
      - General
        - Department of Sociology, 1980-1982 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Expanded Governing Board, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 2)
        - Faculty memoranda, 1980 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - Faculty seminar
          See also: White collar crime.
          - 1976 Mar 1, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 4)
          - 1976 Mar 29, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 5)
          - 1976 Apr 19, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 6)
          - 1976 Apr 30, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 7)
          - 1976 May 10, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 8)
          - 1976 Sep 20, Oct 4, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 9)
          - 1976 Oct 18, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 10)
          - 1976 Nov 22, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 11)
          - 1976 Dec 6, 1976-1976 (Box 24, Folder 12)
          - Participants' list, 1977 (Box 24, Folder 13)
          - 1977 Feb 7, 1977-1977 (Box 24, Folder 14)
          - 1977 Feb 28, 1977-1977 (Box 24, Folder 15)
          - 1977 Mar 28, 1977-1977 (Box 24, Folder 16)
        - Joint degree and other departmental programs, 1972, 1980 (Box 24, Folder 17)
        - Law, Science and Medicine Program, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 18)
        - Registrar's office, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 19)
        - Research Perspectives Study Group, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 20)
        - Yale University Press, 1976-1982 (Box 24, Folder 21-22)
      - Committees
        - Ad Hoc Legal History Discussion Group, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Admissions Committee, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        - Advisory Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
        - Athletic Executive Committee, 1973-1981 (Box 25, Folder 5-7)
        - Athletics Governing Board, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
        - Doctorate in Civil Law (DCL) Committee (Law School), 1979-1981 (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - Education Planning Committee, 1980-1985 (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - Graduate Studies Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - Harry Kalven Prize Committee, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 6)
        - Intensive Semester Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 26, Folder 7)
        - Interdepartmental Programs Committee, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - Legal Studies Committee, 1976-1978 (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - Library Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - Reading Committee, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - University Council Committee on the Social Sciences, Undated (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Course materials
        - Administration of criminal justice, 1981, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - American legal history -- notes, Undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Behavioral science in litigation and legislation, 1975 Spring (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Class notes and Cross Campus Library reading lists, 1979-1981 (Box 27, Folder 4)
        - Course descriptions and schedules
          - 1976-1977 (Box 27, Folder 5)
          - 1978-1979 (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - Criminology
          - Spring term
            - 1974, 1974-1974 (Box 27, Folder 7)
            - 1975, 1975-1975 (Box 27, Folder 8)
          - Course outlines, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 9)
        - Deviant behavior, social control and law, 1979-1980 (Box 27, Folder 10)
        - Field work methods, Undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
        - General theories of crime, Undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
        - Guggenheim Program in Criminal Justice, 1982-1983 (Box 27, Folder 13)
        - Legal Theory Seminar, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 14)
        - Social organization of due process, Undated (Box 27, Folder 15)
        - Social research methods for lawyers
          - 1974-1975 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
          - 1977-1978 (Box 28, Folder 3)
          - 1980, 1980-1980 (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Sociology of law
          - 1973-1974 (Box 28, Folder 5)
          - 1981, 1981-1981 (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Sociology of sport, spring term, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - Sociology textbooks, Undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Writings
    - "All About Sport", 1983 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Ellickson, Robert C., 1984, undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - International peacekeeping -- notes and outline, Undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Licensing bibliography, Undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Noreen Channels' manuscript, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 5-6)
    - Notes on legal indicators, Undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Peer reviews, 1971-1979 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Pilot training program on the use of the behavioral sciences in litigation, 1980 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - "Soccer in Brazil", Undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - "The Social History of American Law", Undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Sociology of Sport Journal, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Sports -- general, Undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - "The Sports Page", 1978-1979 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - "Violence in Sports", 1977 (Box 30, Folder 6)